Guide to the Miriam Frank Oral Histories on Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender, and Queer Activists in the Labor Movement OH.039
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Miriam Frank Oral Histories on Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender, and Queer Activists in the Labor Movement
1994-2009
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Frank, Miriam
OH.039
5.25 Linear Feet in one half manuscript box, 2 card boxes, and 8 cassette boxes. 79 interviews on 144 cassette tapes
In preparation for her 2014 book Out in the Union: A Labor History of Queer America, historian Miriam Frank conducted several oral history interviews with lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and queer labor activists across the United States from 1994-2009. These 79 interviews comprise this oral history collection and cover such topics as family and class identity, the influence of the institutions of the political left and/or the church, and death. Through these interviews, Frank sought to expose individual situations of struggle and to create a detailed history of gay, lesbian, bisexual, transgender, and queer activism in labor unions. Items in this collection have been digitized for researcher use unless otherwise indicated.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Placed on deposit by Dr. Miriam Frank in 1998; the collection plus additional materials were donated by Frank in 2015. The accession numbers related to these gifts are 1998.022 and 2015.022.
Appraisal
Duplicate cassettes of some interviews were deaccessioned because they did not contain original content.
Arrangement
The order in which these materials were sent to the Tamiment Library has been maintained. The tapes are organized alphabetically by last name.
Biographical Note
Miriam Frank's exploration into labor-gay alliances began in 1990 with the publication of a handbook titled Pride at Work: Organizing for Lesbian and Gay Rights in Unions, which she co-authored with her wife Desma Holcomb. This project entailed oral history interviews with New York City activists, which sparked Frank's initiative to delve further into the subject. In 1994 Miriam was awarded New York University's Stephen Charney Vladeck Junior Faculty Fellowship. That year she began conducting interviews in New York City and would travel to six other cities to pursue her research. Her findings eventually culminated in 2014 with the publication of her book Out in the Union: A Labor History of Queer America.
Frank received her B.A., M.A. and PhD from New York University where she served as an Adjunct Professor and Master Teacher of Humanities 1983-2014. She also taught labor history courses at union extension programs in Detroit and New York City, 1977-2009. She is the author of many other publications including The Life and Times of Rosie the Riveter: the story of three million working women during World War II (1982). In 1994 Miriam was awarded New York University's Stephen Charney Vladeck Junior Faculty Fellowship. That year she began conducting interviews in New York City and would travel to six other cities to pursue her research. Her findings eventually culminated in 2014 with the publication of her book Out in the Union: A Labor History of Queer America.
Frank received her B.A., M.A. and PhD from New York University where as of 2018 she is a Master Teacher of Humanities. She has also authored many other publications including The Life and Times of Rosie the Riveter: the story of three million working women during World War II (1982).
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of 79 interviews conducted by Miriam Frank in 1994-2009. Possible alternate spellings of interviewee names and/or pseudonyms are noted in the Scope and Contents note of that interview. Summaries of content are also located in the Scope and Contents note for each tape. These summaries are based on Frank's research notes.
The interviews are both biographical and topical covering such themes as family and class identity, the influence of the political left and/or the church, love, and death. Specific labor topics Frank sought to document were institutional policies and new bargaining issues with regard to lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender and queer workers; the history of gay participation in unions, both hidden and "out"; resistance to LGBTQ workers and activists in some sectors of the labor movement; labor education and AIDS education; the influence of community organizing; and union organizing and collective bargaining in queer community workplaces.
Through these interviews, Frank sought to expose individual situations of struggle and to create a detailed history of LGBTQ activism in the labor movement. In the course of her research, Frank conducted and recorded over 100 interviews, 79 of which are located at the Tamiment Library. Most of these interviews are quoted and indexed in Frank's book Out in the Union: A Labor History of Queer America.
Gay rights -- United States.; Gay liberation movement -- United States.; Lesbians -- Employment -- United States; Gay labor union members |z United States; Oral history.; Homosexuality |x Labor unions |z United States; Discrimination in employment -- United States.; Homosexuality |x Employment |z United States; Gays -- Employment -- United States; Sexual Orientation |z United States; Labor unions -- United States.; Women labor union members -- United States.; Homosexuality -- United States.; Lesbians -- United States; Frank, Miriam
- Tom Ammiano, Apr 7, 1995 (Box 4, Cassette 33, Box 1, Audiocassette OH_039_033)
  Scope and Content Note
  This interview took place in San Francisco, CA. Ammiano was a Teacher of Special Education since 1964 and was a member of the American Federation of Teachers Local 61. His interview discusses the topics of support for gay rights in the California Teachers Association, Bay Area Gay Liberation (BAGL), the Gay Teachers Coalition work with Local 61 officials, Board of Education non-discrimination campaign, labor support "No on 6" (Briggs campaign), curriculum changes, gay/lesbian speakers bureau in schools, Gay Teachers march in Gay Freedom and Labor Day parades, working class/gay identity, lost Board of Education election campaign 1980, stand-up performing, winning of Board seat in 1990, labor endorsements, city politics and his election as Supervisor of City of San Francisco in 1994.
- Anonymous SEIU, Jun 12, 1995 (Box 6, Cassette 87-88, Box 1, Box 7, Audiocassette OH_039_087, OH_039_088)
  This interview took place in Washington D.C. This anonymous interviewee was raised in a Southern town in a racist environment. This interview touches on the topics of class awareness, journalism, VISTA, NOW feminists, her lesbian relationship, SEIU secretary job, coming out to friends, DC lesbian scene, SEIU "Bring a Child to Work Day," not coming out to parents but out in the union, staff union Local 2 OPEIU, domestic partner benefits, SEIU and gay activism, the feature story "Gay Union and Proud" in SEIU national magazine and the positive/negative responses 1993.
  NOTE: Anonymity for reasons of family sensitivity, not union activity.
- Connie Ashbrook, Jul 16, 1995 (Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 095, Cassette 109-110, Box 9, Audiocassette OH_039_109, OH_039_110)
  This interview took place in Portland, OR. Ashbrook was raised in the Midwest and held light industry jobs in the early 1970's. Her interview covers the topics of Ozarks rural commune scene, marriage and divorce, her and lover both school bus drivers, ATU union drive 1977, apprentice truckdriver, harassment, layoff, women's carpenter apprentice program, lesbians/straight women trades network, union meetings UBCJA #1020 (#247), steady work servicing buildings International Union Elevator Constructors #23, elected correspondent to national journal Elevator Constructor, recording secretary labor council delegate, coming out over Prop 9, "No on 13" lunchbox sticker, co-worker reactions, Tradeswomen conference Chicago 1988, Portland Gay Pride march 1993 and 1995 and CLUW and women's involvement in unions.
- Allen Baird, Apr 11, 1995 (Box 1, Box 5, Cassette 51-52, Box 7, Audiocassette OH_039_051, OH_039_052)
  An alternate spelling of this interviewee's first name may be "Allan." This interview took place in San Francisco, CA. At the time of the interview, Baird was a retired president/business representative of newspaper truck drivers Teamster Local 921. A long-time resident of the Castro community, Baird was an advocate of gay/lesbian rights and an activist in Harvey Milk's organization. He was a Local 921 officer in 1962 and was appointed by IBT Western Conference to Local 888 Coors Beer campaign of 1973. His interview discusses the topics of street fights with cartel of Coors distributors, Chinese, Black Panther, Arab and gay community support, Milk's involvement, Coors' biogtry, strength of gay boycott, Teamster hijinks, Coors lie detector policies, Teamster/Farmwork cooperation, IBT internal politics calling off labor boycott, placement of openly gay/lesbian truck drivers, discrimination, legacy of Milk, character in "Harvey Milk" opera of 1995, women's participation in IBT, his activism since retirement, AIDS work in San Francisco, Milk election campaigns, and talk with Jimmy Hoffa about gay labor support in 1974.
- Tom Barbera, Apr 14, 2000 (Box 4, Cassette 131-132, Box 1, Box 9, Audiocassette OH_039_141, OH_039_142)
  This interview took place in Boston, MA.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  This interview is currently being digitized. An access CD is not yet available.
- Nancy Brown, May 1, 1995 (Box 5, Cassette 70-71, Box 1, Box 7, Audiocassette OH_039_070, OH_039_071)
  This interview took place in Royal Oak (Detroit). Brown was raised in Detroit and Kalamazoo in an Air Force military family. Her interview discusses the topics of her job at the post office in the late 1960's, NALC and sexism, her promotion to supervisor and detachment from harassment, co-worker lesbian relationship, lesbian scene mid-1970's, gay/straight friendships, construction site work culture, comments of racism and homphobia, electrician apprenticeship Local 58 IBEW, sexism at union meetings and at work site, earning respect and finding allies, Detroit Women in Trades, Local 58 union life, union benefits and equity for construction workers' domestic partners.
- Becky Capoferri, Jul 17, 1995 (Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 095, Cassette 111-112, Box 9, Audiocassette OH_039_111, OH_039_112)
  This interview took place in Portland, OR. Capoferri was raised in Springfield, OH in a business family. Her interview covers the topics of teenage consciousness of bisexuality, counterculture late 1960's, dropping out of high school, marriage and daughter, mental health work, active OPEU #503 (SEIU) psychiatric aide, gay membership and gay executive council, pay equity strike, non-discrimination in contract, state executive order and origins of Oregon Citizens Alliance anti0gay campaigns 1987, queer identity, OPEU staff 1989, "No on 9" union work, Bob Ralphs' leadership, Oregon Lavendar Labor Action Committee, building queer/Latina coalition HERE #4, defeat of Prop 9 1992, marijuana withdrawl, OPEU strike Spring 1995, NW union women conference queer caucus, queer/labor agenda, and class politics/queer community.
- Donna Cartwright, Jul 16, 2001 (Box 4, Cassette 133-135, Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 086, Audiocassette not numbered)
- Gerry Casey, Mar 27, 1995 (Box 1, Box 4, Cassette 30, Box 8, Audiocassette OH_039_030)
  This interview took place in Boston, MA. Casey grew up in Methuen and was a political activist in the 1960's, a state social worker, and a member of the Local 509 Service Employees union. Her interview discusses the topics of coming out in the early 1970's, non-political friendships, gender and union power, domestic partner benefits in 1994, rank and file gay formations, compulsive union activism, alcoholism, and support from union co-workers during her detox/rehabilitation.
- Shirley Clarke, Mar 27, 1995 (Box 1, Box 8, Audiocassette OH_039_031, OH_039_032)
  This interview took place in Boston, MA. Clarke spent her childhood in an African American community and experiences sexual abuse by the matrons at her orphanage. She recounts her experiences in foster homes and getting punished for lesbian behavior. She eventually took a housekeeper job at the Statler hilton and joined the Hotel and Restaurant Local 26 union. When she moved back to Boston, she took a state job and joined AFSCME Local 402. Her interview discusses the topics of butch identity, civil rights, her involvement in marches on Washington and Selma, her son's participation in Head Start, community activism, her inter-racial butch/femme marriage of 7 years, Chicago lesbian scene, mid-1970's community mental work, workplace gay culture, union support of gay rights, Washington ACT-UP lock-up, her election as Local 402 Vice President despite gay baiting, gay activists at AFSCME conventions, Local 509 SEIU, Baltimore SEIU Lavendar Caucus conference 1992 and lesbian/black/union family life.
- Shelly Crites, Jul 14, 1995 (Box 6, Cassette 106, Box 1, Box 9, Audiocassette OH_039_106)
  This interview took place in Seattle. Crites was raised in Kansas City and had a drafting job. Her interview discusses the topics of radical politics, SDS Women's caucus, gay liberation, Peace and Freedom Party, International Socialists in the early 1970's, conflict of labor organizing/gay liberation politics, school bus driver of 75 workers, veteran lesbian drivers and their networks, workday and culture of the dispatch office, lesbian identity and worklife, relation of shop to Teamster union, marginal job, safety issues, driving special needs kids, getting hired at xerox/print shop 1973, acquiring commercial print skills, sexism in new press shop, ten years in trade before member of printers union Printing Pressman #39, Graphic Communications union 1982, Seattle reproductive rights activist, open about feminism on job, less open about lesbian identity but printed "No on 13" poster 1978.
- Ginny Cutting, Mar 24,1995 (Box 1, Box 4, Cassette 25-26, Box 8, Audiocassette OH_039_025, OH_039_026)
  This interview took place in Boston, MA. Cutting was raised in a union fmaily in Somerville. Her father was a Teamsters trucker Local 25. She was an organizer for the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers Local 2222 throughout New England. Her interview covers the topics of empowering women workers, CLUW, conservatism of workers, her enrollment in the University of Massachusetts, coming out through women's softball, lesbian sports culture, her job as a State of Massachusetts AIDS caseworker, her membership in the Service Employees Local 509 union, Yvonne Forrest, gay culture of state workers, her position on the Executive Board of Gay and Lesbian Concerns Committee, GALLAN's Fenway Benefit, her father's death and Boston working class identity.
- Gary Deane, Aug 9, 1994 (Box 3, Box 1, Box 4, Cassette 2-3, Box 8, Audiocassette OH_039_002, OH_039_003)
  Existence and Location of Copies
  A transcript of this interview is available at the Tamiment Library.
  This interview took place in New York City. Gary Deane was raised in Cincinatti, OH with a seminary education. After pursuing a secular college education, Deane came out just before the draft board examination and "1-Y" classification. He was an officer of the Cincinatti NAACP and was an activist in the fair housing movement in the Midwest. He participated in civil rights campaigns to integrate construction unions and mid-1960's cooperative housing projects of the Chicago Joint Board of Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. Deane was also an openly gay candidate in the 1977 campaign for City Council Brooklyn delegate-at-large and was involved in the founding of the Brooklyn Lambda Independent Democrats. His interview touches on the topics of gay life in Chicago, social life, gay identity in ACWA, conflicts with leadership, career in NYC cooperative housing and activity in NYC Liberal Party.
- Ramon de la Fuente, Jun 10, 1995 (Box 1, Box 6, Cassette 83-84, Box 7, Audiocassette OH_039_083, OH_039_084)
  This interview took place in Washington D.C. De la Fuente was raised in Manila as a Filipino Catholic. His interview discusses the topics of immigration to Philadelphia, speaking Spanish/Tugalog, immigrant culture, secular world 1970's, early gay awareness, language difficulties, ethnic hierarchies, gay bars Philadelphia/Atlantic City, apprenticeship at NASSCO San Diego Navy shipyard 1979, shipyard electrician erotic subculture, homphobia, religious crisis, Fransciscan seminary, fournalism training BNA, active steward Newspaper Guild Local 39, Asian production workers BNA, founder APALA (Asian Pacific AFL-CIO), and BNA domestic partner benefits TNG contract.
- Robert G. De Santis, Jun 29, 1996 (Box 4, Cassette 136, Box 1, Box 9, Audiocassette OH_039_129)
  This interview took place in Oakland, CA.
- Michael Dias, Apr 29, 1995 (Box 5, Cassette 64, Box 1, Box 7, Audiocassette OH_039_064)
  This interview took place in Boston (Detroit). Dias was raised in New Bedford in a Portugese immigrant family. His interview covers the topics of early gay consciousness, navy service as ship's barber, harassment of gay sailors, special education training, non-union state jobs, gay life in Boston in the 1970's, motorcycle leather scene, gay baiting on job, gay theater troupe, SEIU Local 509 1989 steward, his recruitment by Ginny Cutting to the Gay and Lesbian Concern Committee (Lavendar Caucus), coming out on the job, defending gay members and gay identity in union.
- Gary Dotterman, Mar 23, 1995 (Box 1, Box 4, Cassette 19-20, Box 8, Audiocassette OH_039_019, OH_039_020)
  This interview took place in Boston, MA. Dotterman was raised in Tulsa in the late 1940's in a union family. His interview covers the topics of work in local Democratic clubs, volunteering in the 1960 JFK campaign, the African American community in Tulsa, CORE, Freedom Summer, Vietnam service, criticism of US policy, military investigation, suppression of gay urges, contact with Soviet officials, Arthur Goldberg, 1966 anti-war demonstrations in Tulsa, Bobby Kennedy campaigns, National Welfare Rights Organization, march on Wisconsin legislature, NYC Jews for Urban Justice, contact with gay rap groups, early 1970's Dump Nixon with Allard Loewenstein, McGovern campaign, coming out in Boston, 1970's bar scene as bouncer at The Other Side, lobbying for gay rights, Sylvia Sidney, class consciousness, working as an aide to Councilman David Skondras, Coors boycott mid-1980's, housing advocacy HERE Local 26, and 1986 Communist Party membership.
- Madelyn Elder, Jul 17, 1995 (Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 095, Cassette 113, Box 9, Audiocassette OH_039_113)
  This interview took place in Portland, OR. Elder was raised in smalltown Central Illinois in a pro-labor professional family. Her interview discusses the topics of high school feminism, gay liberation early 1970's, union job CWA Ann Arbor, search for left politics in Detroit mid-1970's, Seattle Radical Women 1977-1986, chief steward organizing safety wildcat CWA #9102 (later 7800) 1980, Seattle Initiative 13 and controversy over coalition work in CWA local union and King County Labor Council: non-traditional women workers dyke baited, anti-gay members, CWA #9102 discriminated gay comrade Jonathon Foe Freedom Socialist telephone intaller shop steward, Radical Women work, CWA delegate Labor Council, move to Portland for Radical Women 1986, shop steward CWA #7901, No on 9 plant gate organizing with gay machinist Joe Keir, No on 13 grassroots campaign, gay neutrality Prop 8 public employees rights, and community coalition Progressive Queers 1994-1995.
- Shelley Ettinger, Sep 11, 1998 (Box 4, Cassette 137-138, Box 1, Box 9, Audiocassette OH_039_136, OH_039_137)
  This interview took place in New York City.
- Tess Ewing, Mar 25, 1995 (Box 1, Box 4, Cassette 27-28, Box 8, Audiocassette OH_039_027, OH_039_028)
  This interview took place in Boston, MA. Ewing had a middle class upbringing in Swampscott, MA. She came out in 1970 in the women's movement Bread & Roses. Her interview covers the topics of tenant activism, skilled labor, a union drive led by her lover at the Pre-Term Abortion Clinic, school bus drivers organizing with Teamsters 829 in 1976, Workers World and Teamsters/Amalgamated Transit jurisdictional dispute leading to chartering Steelworkers 8751, sexism, lesbian presence in bus yard, lesbian work-place culture, GALLAN, Central America activism, and lesbian caucus Women's Institute for Leadership Development (WILD) 1988.
- Gerry Faier, Feb 13, 1995 (Box 1, Box 4, Cassette 6-7, Box 8, Audiocassette OH_039_007, OH_039_007)
  This interview took place in New York City. Gerry Faier was born in 1908 to Russian Orthodox Jewish immigants in Boro Park. Faier educated herself at the New York Public Library and eventually became the leader of the Boro Park Unemployment Council and a member of the Communist Party. In her attempts for employment at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, Faier was blackballed for being a communist. Her interview discusses the topics of rebellion against family, being a welfare recipient, activity with a clandestine social workers union, her life and love with an older Catholic man, coming out in Woodstock artist bar, her friendship with artists such as Franz Kline and writers such as James Baldwin, comfort with underground gay life, the bars in the Village, and her involvement as a founding member of Senior Action in a Gay Environment (SAGE).
- James N. Green, Jan 10, 1997 (Box 4, Cassette 126-127, Box 1, Box 9, Audiocassette OH_039_132, OH_039_133)
- Jackie Harris, Mar 1, 1995 (Box 1, Box 4, Cassette 11-12, Box 8, Audiocassette OH_039_011, OH_039_012)
  This interview took place in New York City. Jackie Harris grew up in Brooklyn, NY as a tomboy with a heritage of union respect in her African American family. She was involved in the civil rights and black power movements in the 1960's as well as the March on Washington of 1963. Her first union membership came as a social caseworker in Local 371, DC 37 ASFSCME. Her interview covers the topics of racial oppresion, interracial relationships, social life with gay house parties, black people in the gay world, CORE activity, picketing Woolworths, Communist Party circles, her visit to Cuba in the early 1960's, FBI harrassment, activity in strike of 1967, division of work and social life with gay co-workers, promotions at job, her election as local delegate, and fiscal malfeasance in union hierarchy.
- Karin Hart, Apr 7, 1995 (Box 4, Cassette 36-37, Box 1, Box 8, Audiocassette OH_039_036, OH_039_037)